If you have tried direct pressure and wound packing, but the bleeding on an arm or leg just won't stop, it is potentially life-threatening situation.
In this case, for anyone age 2 and older, we need to move quickly to apply a tourniquet.
For children under the age of 2, remember to continue using direct pressure instead.
Your instructor will demonstrate and pass out tourniquets so you can practice together.
To apply a tourniquet, first place the tourniquet 2 to 3 inches above the wound, making sure you aren't placing it directly over a joint like an elbow or knee.
Pull the strap as tight as you possibly can and secure it.
Then, you'll turn the windlass, that's the stick-like rod on the device, until the bleeding completely stops.
Once it's secure, your final step is to record the exact time you put it on.
This is vital information for the surgeons who will treat the person later.
Most importantly, once that tourniquet is on, do not take it off for any reason.
Only a doctor in a hospital should do that.
For our practice today, I want you to apply the tourniquet to your own arm or leg.
You don't need to tighten it to the point of stopping blood flow, but I want you to tighten the strap until you feel firm pressure,
and then give the windlass a few turns until you feel that pressure increase.
Once you've felt how the mechanism works, you can take it off and go ahead and dispose of your used gauze squares and rolls.
Finally, removing your gloves in the proper manner helps to keep ourselves safe from contamination.
Using your dominant hand, pinch the outside of the opposite glove near the wrist, being careful not to touch your skin,
and peel it downward so it turns inside out as it comes off.
Hold that crumpled glove in your still-gloved hand.
Now, slide the fingers of your clean hand under the wrist cuff of the remaining glove and peel it off over the first one.
This should leave both gloves inside out and nested together.
Drop them straight into the biohazard container and immediately wash your hands with soap and water for at least 30 seconds.